Public Works of Art Project selected administrative and business records
Archives of American Art
Public Works of Art Project selected administrative and business records
1933-1936
Archives of American Art
Public Works of Art Project
AAA.publworr
Archival Resource Key
18 Microfilm reels
Conditions Governing Access
Patrons must use microfilm copy.
Scope and Contents
Selected records of the PWAP include the following series: Central Office (Washington, D.C.) Correspondence and Related Records, including progress reports, minutes of meetings, and finance records (reels DC1-3); Correspondence and Personal Files of Edward P. Rowan, Technical Director (reels DC3-4); Central Office Correspondence With Artists (reels DC5-7); Central Office Files and Publicity Materials, including correspondence of project director Edward Bruce (reel DC8); Newspaper Clippings (reels DC8-9); Correspondence and Related records of Cecil Jones, Business Director (reels DC9-12); Final Reports on Projects, Report Materials and Project Issuances (reel DC12); Regional Office Records (reels DC12-13); and selected Correspondence of the New York Regional Office (Region 2) With Artists concerning administrative details of employing artists (DC 112-115).
Existence and Location of Copies
35mm microfilm reels DC1-DC13 and DC112-DC115 available for use at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan.
Existence and Location of Originals
Originals in the National Archives, Records of the Public Building Service, record group 121, entries 106-111 and 114-117.
Biographical / Historical
The Public Works of Art Project (PWAP), the first of the New Deal art programs, was established under the Department of the Treasury in December 1933 to assist unemployed artists by enabling them to work on the decoration of non-federal public buildings. Although it lasted only until the following summer, it engaged nearly 4,000 artists in all parts of the country and served as an important precedent for subsequent federal art programs, such as the Federal Art Project of the Works Progress Administration. Later art projects administered under the Department of the Treasury were the Section of Fine Arts, originally the Section of Painting and Sculpture, and the Treasury Relief Art Project, both of which served to employ artists to decorate federal buildings across the United States.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Series microfilmed by AAA were selected from the National Archives record group 121, Records of the Public Buildings Service. Additional records of the PWAP are preserved at the National Archives. Series which were not microfilmed include: correspondence of L.W. Roberts, assistant secretary of the Treasury; the central file of the Advisory Committee and the Project; card lists of allocated paintings and other works of art; and receipt cards for works of art.
Related Materials
AAA has filmed, and described separately, selected records of the Treasury Relief Art Project (reels DC14-38) and the Section of Fine Arts (reels DC38-43) from record group 121. In addition, selected records of the WPA Federal Art Project (National Archives record group 69) were also filmed (reels DC44-DC111 and DC129-130).
New Deal, 1933-1939; Federal aid to the arts; Federal aid to public welfare; Programs (organizations); Agencies; Bruce, Edward, 1879-1943; Rowan, Edward Beatty, 1898-1946; United States. Department of the Treasury; Jones, Cecil H.
- Central office (Washington, D.C.) records, 1933-1935; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 3 Microfilm reels
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by folder heading (names and subjects combined).
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence, progress and other reports, minutes of meetings, official circulars and letters, personnel and financial records, press releases, and other records relating to the policies, organization, and activities of the Project. A small quantity of records concerns early meetings of the Advisory Committee to the Treasury on Fine Arts which were apparently made a part of this series when it was set up by the Project. Central office correspondence with artists is a separate series (reels DC5-7), described separately.
  - Organization, PWAP, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC001, Frame 1-54)
  - Organization, closing PWAP, Corcoran, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC001, Frame 55-120)
  - Lists, Artists, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC001, Frame 121-170)
  - Lists, Administrative, PWAP Bulletin, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC001, Frame 171-232)
  - Lists of photographs, finances, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC001, Frame 233-349)
  - Organization, Administration, PWAP, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC001, Frame 350-642)
  - Organization, End PWAP, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC001, Frame 643-825)
  - Correspondence, organization, women artists, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC001, Frame 826-942)
  - List, murals, location, artists, justice department, P.O. murals, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC001, Frame 943-1002)
  - Justice, P.O. buildings-decoration, CCC Correspondence, 1934-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC002, Frame 1-386)
  - Lists, works, artists, Corcoran, PWAP, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC002, Frame 387-463)
  - Administration - national, PWAP, regional, miscellaneous, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC002, Frame 464-637)
  - Indians, PWAP policy re. Indians, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC002, Frame 638-762)
  - "Information on Artists'' file PWAP, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC002, Frame 763-825)
  - Formal CWA Procedure, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC002, Frame 826-900)
  - FERA organization, PWAP, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC002, Frame 901-1156)
  - List PWAP Artists, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC002, Frame 1157-1218)
  - Central office (Washington, D.C.) records, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC003)
- Correspondence and personal files of Edward B. Rowan, 1934-1935; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.8 Linear feet 2 partial microfilm reels
  Correspondence with prominent artists concerning ways and means of employing unemployed artists; correspondence with artists in the regions, critical evaluations of art produced under the PWAP; copies of articles written by Rowan, and various administrative and reference materials. Rowan was the assistant technical director of the PWAP. He worked closely with Edward Bruce, the director of the PWAP.
  - Correspondence and personal files, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC003)
  - Correspondence and personal files, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC004)
- Central office (Washington, D.C.) correspondence with artists, 1933-1935; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 3 Microfilm reels
  With few exceptions, files are arranged alphabetically by correspondent, thereunder chronologically.
  Copies of letters sent to artists in all regions and letters received, concerning problems and individual projects of the artists. Some widely divergent comments on the existent art relief program are expressed in many of the letters.
  - A, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC005, Frame 1-61)
  - B, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC005, Frame 62-343)
  - C, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC005, Frame 344-595)
  - D, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC005, Frame 596-821)
  - E, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC005, Frame 822-856)
  - F, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC005, Frame 857-979)
  - G, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC005, Frame 980-1107)
  - H, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC005, Frame 1108-1193)
  - Ho., 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC006, Frame 1-67)
  - I, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC006, Frame 68-79)
  - J, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC006, Frame 80-156)
  - K, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC006, Frame 157-294)
  - L, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC006, Frame 295-430)
  - M, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC006, Frame 431-674)
  - N, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC006, Frame 675-710)
  - O, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC006, Frame 711-743)
  - P, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC006, Frame 744-853)
  - Q, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC006, Frame 854-945)
  - R, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC006, Frame 946-1187)
  - S, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC007, Frame 1-31)
  - T, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC007, Frame 32-159)
  - U, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC007, Frame 160-173)
  - V, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC007, Frame 174-205)
  - W, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC007, Frame 206-397)
  - Y, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC007, Frame 398-413)
  - Z, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC007, Frame 414-439)
  - Important PWAP correspondence, 1933-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC007, Frame 440-531)
    Not listed alphabetically. Extracts from artists letters, boards of education,artists organizations, also regional chairmen and committees.
- Correspondence and related records of Cecil Jones, 1933-1934; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot 4 microfilm reels
  Arranged by region, thereunder, chronologically.
  Letters, telegrams and memoranda received from and copies sent to the regional offices and others in the regions; interoffice memoranda; periodic and statistical reports; and minor fiscal records. Cecil Jones was the business director of the PWAP.
  - Cecil Jones Correspondence and Washington, D.C.-N.E. Administration and Finances, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC009, Frame 957-1208)
  - Administrative correspondence between Cecil H. Jones and offices of Region 1, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC010, Frame 1-160)
  - Administrative correspondence between Cecil H. Jones and offices of Region 2, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC010, Frame 161-541, 582-799)
  - Settling of PWAP accounts, Treasury Department statements, Payment of artists, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC010, Frame 542-581)
  - Administrative correspondence between Cecil H. Jones and offices of Region 3, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC010, Frame 800-948)
  - Administrative correspondence from Cecil H. Jones to regional offices, agencies, Washington, D.C., 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC010, Frame 949-1252)
  - Administrative correspondence of Edward Bruce, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC010, Frame 1253-1266)
  - Correspondence of PWAP Administrative office with various regional offices, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC011, Frame 1-618)
  - Correspondence with offices of Region 11, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC011, Frame 619-707)
  - Correspondence with offices of Region 12, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC011, Frame 708-872)
  - Correspondence with offices of Region 13, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC011, Frame 873-1131)
  - Correspondence with offices of Region 14, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC011, Frame 1132-1380)
  - Correspondence with offices of Region 15, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC011, Frame 1381-1483)
  - Cecil H. Jones correspondence with offices (General business and finance) of Region 15, 1934-10; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC012, Frame 1-230)
  - Cecil H. Jones correspondence with offices (General business and finance) of Region 16, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC012, Frame 231-504)
- PWAP newspaper clippings, 1933-1934; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot 2 partial microfilm reels
  Arranged in two groups: November 1933-February 1934 and February 1934-October 1934. Arranged thereunder by region, and thereunder, chronologically.
  Newspaper clippings relating to the activities of the PWAP specifically at the regional level, November 1933-October 1934.
  - Press clippings, Ann Cranton Trip, South and West, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 831-873)
  - Press clippings, New England and NYC, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 873-930)
  - Press clippings, Washington, D.C. and Penn., 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 931-1053)
  - Press clippings, South, Midwest, Pittsburgh, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 1054-1109)
  - Press clippings, 1933-12-1934-03; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC009, Frame 1-126)
  - Press clippings, Articles, 1933-12-1934-02; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC009, Frame 127-210)
  - Press clippings, New England, NYC, NY, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC009, Frame 211-266)
  - Press clippings, Washington, D.C., 1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC009, Frame 257-490)
  - Press clippings, South, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC009, Frame 491-540)
  - Press clippings, Midwest: Mo., Neb.,Kan., Iowa, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC009, Frame 541-568)
  - Press clippings, Midwest: Cleveland, Pittsburgh, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC009, Frame 569-638)
  - Press clippings, Ill., Minn., Wisc., 1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC009, Frame 639-651)
  - Press clippings, Ariz., Texas, N.M., Colorado, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC009, Frame 652-689)
  - Press clippings, S. Calif., L.A., 1934-1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC009, Frame 690-737)
  - Press clippings, Second Half of 1934/Sand Francisco, Utah, Archival Resource Key (Reel DC009, Frame 738-807)
  - Press clippings, First Half of 1934/ N. California and Utah, Archival Resource Key (Reel DC009, Frame 808-947)
  - Press clippings, catalogues, Oregon, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC009, Frame 948-955)
- Central office (Washington, D.C.) files and publicity materials, 1933-1934; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet 1 partial microfilm reel
  File of publicity materials: arranged alphabetically by subject.
  Miscellaneous central office files include: correspondence of Edward Bruce, primarily concerning certain art exhibits; lists of works of art, some showing their final disposition; and miscellaneous correspondence with regional office personnel and artists in the field. The file of publicity materials contains: photocopied press releases and bulletins issued by the Project; copies of magazine articles written by Project employees; and a variety of unsolicited comments and news concerning Project activities, including news clippings, editorials, magazine articles, and speeches.
  - Administration, Finance, Publications, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 1-31)
  - Artist's Subsistenece Homestead, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 32-89)
  - Corcoran exhibition correspondence, 1934-04-1934-05; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 90-177)
  - Corcoran Exhibition List, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 2478-183)
  - List, Allocation, Region 6, Ala., Ark., L.A., MIss, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 184-188)
  - List, Allocation, Region 10, Ill., Wisc., Minn. to Wash, D.C., 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 189-200)
  - Lists, Artists and works, Regions 10-16, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 201-217)
  - Lists, Works, Regions 3-9, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 218-231)
  - Lists, Works, Region 2, New York, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 232-240)
  - Lists, Works, Region 1, New England, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 241-244)
  - Return of work from Corcoran Exhibition, 1934-05-1934-06; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 245-279)
  - List, Work returned to Philadelphia, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 280-282)
  - Lists, Work returned to regions 1-5, 7-9,12,14-15, Cleveland, NYC, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 283-295)
  - List, Works returned or allocated to NYC and regions, 1,5,14-16, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 296-303)
  - List, Allocation of works, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 304-308)
  - Lists, Miscellaneous (5), 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 309-325)
  - Lists, Work sent to Washington, D.C. for Corcoran Exhibition, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 326- ?)
  - Correspondence urging extension of PWAP (Maryland and Pennsylvania), 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 361-389)
  - Hazel Clere correspondence, Washington, DC office, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 390-502)
  - Stuart T. Williams controversy, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 503-537)
  - Publicity Materials, Corcoran Exhibition, and F.D.R. choices, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008)
  - Miscellaneous administrative and organizational (Press releases, minutes and publicity), 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 567-610)
  - Press clippings and miscellaneous (Coit Towers and Paul Cadmus), 1934-02-1934-07; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 656-752)
  - Magazine articles relating to PWAP, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 753-797)
  - Region 14, N. & S. California, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 798-806)
  - Indian Artists (Indians at Work), 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC008, Frame 807-830)
- Final reports, report materials and project issuances, 1933-1936; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet One partial microfilm reel
  A printed copy of the report of the Assistant of the Treasury to the Federal Relief Administrator for the period December 8, 1933 to June 30, 1934; a typewritten copy of a report covering the PWAP activities and liquidation for the period October 1, 1934 to June 22, 1935; narrative, statistical and other records used in preparation of the reports; reference material supplementing the information in the reports.
  - PWAP drafts of final report, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC012, Frame 505-541)
  - Miscellaneous lists including one of PWAP projects by region, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC012, Frame 542-575)
  - ECW artists, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC012, Frame 576-584)
  - PWAP bulletin #14, 1934-02; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC012, Frame 585-592)
  - Interim report, TRAP, 1936-05-01; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC012, Frame 395-092)
  - Interim report, TRAP, Summary of Contents, 1936-05-01; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC012, Frame 594)
  - Interim report, TRAP, Draft of PWAP, Final report, plus rough draft with some corrections, 1936-05-01; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC012, Frame 633-778)
  - Correspondence, lists collected for PWAP, Final report, dated first half 1934, Archival Resource Key (Reel DC012, Frame 779-957)
- Regional office records, 1933-1934; Series 8; Archival Resource Key; 2 Microfilm reels
  Arranged by region.
  A selection of records from central files of the 16 regional offices (the bulk of this material has been disposed of), consists of correspondence, telegrams, and memoranda of an administrative character; minutes of meetings; a few records relating to personnel; charts and statistics; records relating to individual projects, including lists of finished works; and a variety of technical and other reference materials. Activities of committees and subcommittees in the regions are also documented insofar as any records of importance concerning them could be located.
  - Region 4, 1933-12-1934-07; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC012, Frame 958-1440)
  - Region 10, 1933-12-1934-07; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC013, Frame 119-165)
  - Region 13, undated; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC013, Frame 166-172)
  - Region 12, 1933-12-1934-11; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC013, Frame 173-728)
  - Regions 6, 12, 13 and 14, undated; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC013, Frame 252-262)
  - Southern States Art League, undated; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC013, Frame 265-266)
  - Region 1, 1933-12-1934-05; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC013, Frame 729-824)
  - Region 2, 1932-11-1934-04; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC013, Frame 825-1140)
  - Region 14, 1933-12-1934-05; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC013, Frame 1141-1307)
  - Region 16, 1933-12-1934-09; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC013, Frame 1308-1510)
- Correspondence of the New York (Region 2) office with artists, 1933-1934; Series 9; Archival Resource Key; 4 Linear feet 4 microfilm reels
  Correspondence retained as an example of regional correspondence with artists includes letters dealing with administrative details important to employing artists, the initiation and execution of the individual art projects, and technical and artistic matters; special reports, reference material, and other matter is enclosed with the letters.
  - Correspondence of the New York (Region 2) office with artists, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC112)
  - Correspondence of the New York (Region 2) office with artists, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC113)
  - Correspondence of the New York (Region 2) office with artists, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC114)
  - Correspondence of the New York (Region 2) office with artists, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel DC115)